What is life?
生命是什么？
Like most great questions, this one is easy to ask but difficult to answer.
和大多数重大问题一样，这个问题问起来容易，回答起来却很难。
The reason is simple: we know of just one type of life and it’s challenging to do science with a sample size of one.
原因很简单：我们只知道一种生命，而在样本量只有一个的情况下做科学研究很有挑战性。
The field of artificial life — called ALife for short — is the systematic attempt to spell out life’s fundamental principles.
人工生命（简称ALife）这一领域，是一种系统性的尝试，旨在阐明生命的基本原理。
Many of its practitioners, so-called ALifers, think that somehow making life is the surest way to really understand what life is.
该领域的许多从业者，也就是所谓的ALifer（人工生命研究者），认为设法造出生命是真正理解生命为何物的最可靠途径。
So far no one has convincingly made artificial life.
迄今为止，还没有人令人信服地造出人工生命。
This track record makes ALife a ripe target for criticism, such as declarations of the field’s doubtful scientific value.
这样的过往记录使ALife成了现成的批评靶子，比如有人宣称这一领域的科学价值值得怀疑。
Alan Smith, a complexity scientist, is tired of such complaints.
复杂性科学家艾伦·史密斯已经厌倦了这类抱怨。
Asking about “the point” of ALife might be, well, missing the point entirely, he says.
他说，追问ALife有什么“意义”，或许，嗯，完全没抓住要点。
“The existence of a living system is not about the use of anything,” Alan says.
“生命系统的存在与它有没有用无关，”艾伦说。
“Some people ask me, ‘So what’s the worth of artificial life?’
“有人问我：‘那么，人工生命有什么价值呢？’
Do you ever think, ‘What is the worth of your grandmother?’”
你会不会去想：‘你祖母有什么价值？’”
As much as many ALifers hate emphasizing their research’s applications, the attempts to create artificial life could have practical payoffs.
尽管许多ALifer很不愿意强调自己研究的应用，但创造人工生命的尝试有可能带来实际的回报。
Artificial intelligence may be considered ALife’s cousin in that researchers in both fields are enamored with a concept called open-ended evolution.
人工智能或许可以看作ALife的“表亲”，因为这两个领域的研究者都迷恋一个叫作“开放式演化”的概念。
This is the capacity for a system to create essentially endless complexity, to be a sort of “novelty generator”.
这指的是一个系统创造出近乎无穷无尽的复杂性、成为某种“新奇事物生成器”的能力。
The only system known to exhibit this is Earth’s biosphere.
已知唯一能表现出这种能力的系统是地球的生物圈。
If the field of ALife manages to reproduce life’s endless “creativity” in some virtual model, those same principles could give rise to truly inventive machines.
如果ALife领域能够在某个虚拟模型中重现生命无穷无尽的“创造力”，那么同样的原理就可能催生出真正富有创造性的机器。
Compared with developments in AI, advances in ALife are harder to recognize.
与人工智能的发展相比，ALife的进展更难辨识。
One reason is that ALife is a field in which the central concept — life itself — is undefined.
原因之一在于，ALife这一领域的核心概念——生命本身——尚无定义。
The lack of agreement among ALifers doesn’t help either.
ALifer之间缺乏共识，这也无济于事。
The result is a diverse range of projects that each advance along their unique paths.
结果就是出现了各种各样的项目，每个项目都沿着自己独特的道路推进。
For better or worse, ALife mirrors the very subject it studies.
不论是好是坏，ALife都恰恰映照出它所研究的对象本身。
Its muddled progression is a striking parallel to the evolutionary struggles that have shaped Earth’s biosphere.
它混乱的发展历程，与生物演化中塑造了地球生物圈的种种艰难挣扎惊人地相似。
Undefined and uncontrolled, ALife drives its followers to repurpose old ideas and generate novelty.
ALife既无定义，又不受控制，这驱使其追随者为旧观念找到新用途，并创造出新奇事物。
It may be, of course, that these characteristics aren’t in any way surprising or singular.
当然，也可能这些特点丝毫不令人惊讶，也并非独一无二。
They may apply universally to all acts of evolution.
它们可能普遍适用于一切演化活动。
Ultimately ALife may be nothing special.
归根结底，ALife可能并没有什么特别之处。
But even this dismissal suggests something: perhaps, just like life itself throughout the universe, the rise of ALife will prove unavoidable.
但即便是这种否定也说明了一点：或许，就像生命本身在整个宇宙中的兴起一样，ALife的兴起终将被证明是不可避免的。